Nicholas G. McMullen

Certified Compensation & Human Resources Professional nicholasgmcmullen@gmail.com

Summary

Analytically-inclined, people-oriented HR practitioner with experience supporting executives and front-line teams as a strategic partner. Skilled in compensation design and management, people analytics, human resources operations, and onboarding. Experience implementing, integrating, and managing a variety of HR technology solutions, architecting compensation programs, and leading people-people teams.

Employment

RStudio PBC

RStudio PBC is a software development company and certified Public Benefit Corporation that builds and maintains enterprise and open-source tools for data science with R and Python.

Compensation & People Analytics Lead

January 2022 - Present

- Lead all aspects of RStudio's compensation operations, administration, and design including base salary, short-term incentive (STI), long-term incentive (LTI)
- Assist in the analysis and design of executive compensation programs and incentives
- Participate in salary surveys, benchmark jobs to align with compensation philosophy
- Manage cadenced departmental compensation reviews with executives
- Approve compensation for all external job offers, promotions, and internal transfers
- Build, automate dashboards using R/RStudio/shiny to provide automated, people-related insights to executives
- Configure HR systems to meet company needs and liaise with IT to ensure accurate, secure transfer of data between systems

People Operations Partner

January 2021 - January 2022

- Built career framework and aligned to salary structures for engineering department
- Conducted job analysis and market pricing of all company jobs
- Assisted in the implementation and company-wide rollout of new HRIS
- Acted as the initial point of contact for employee relations issues
- Trained and coached small groups of managers on effective management practices

WorldatWork Total Rewards Association

WorldatWork is the world's foremost total rewards association, providing professional credentialing, education, and research to a broad global network of human resources professionals.

Senior Specialist, Total Rewards Content

September 2020 - January 2021

- Delivered a preliminary People Analytics practice strategy to association leadership
- Conducted competitive market research in the people analytics education market
- Advised practice leaders on trends, opportunities, and threats in total rewards

Alliance Residential Company

Alliance Residential company is a 4000+ employee multifamily property management and development company, based in Phoenix, Arizona with a presence in 20+ US states. Property Management division acquired by Greystar Real Estate Partners in July 2020.

Manager, People Systems & Analytics

January 2020 - September 2020

- Oversaw operation of all human resources information systems including HRIS (UltiPro), ATS (iCIMS), Compensation (Salary.com), and LMS (Fuse LXP)
- Led implementation of new organizational corporate social responsibility platform
- Conducted job analysis and evaluation of all company jobs
- Administered Quarterly Incentive Program, including building code-based distribution and audit capabilities
- Evaluated effectiveness of HR programs and field performance using R and RStudio and presented findings to executives

Manager, Talent Analytics & Operations

May 2018 - January 2020

- Oversaw operation of human resources information systems including ATS (iCIMS),
 Compensation (Salary.com), and LMS (Cornerstone OnDemand & Fuse LXP)
- Led implementation of Fuse LXP and company-wide conversion from Cornerstone OnDemand LMS
- Managed Talent Coordinator team responsible for pre-hire onboarding tasks and workflows including offer letters, compliance, and queuing profiles for import to HRIS
- Automated recruiting billback process, including integrating data sources from CRM, ATS, and HRIS and utilizing open source R tools, saving 30+ hours of manual work per month
- Developed suite of automated Tableau dashboards to support monthly reporting needs of Talent executive team

Learning & Development Intern

June 2017 - August 2017

- Assisted with administration and management of Cornerstone OnDemand LMS
- Built and distributed reports required by the field Learning and Development team
- Analyzed training program data for business impact and presented results to executive team

Education

Macalester College

Applied Mathematics and Statistics, B.A. magna cum laude

Certifications

Certified Compensation Professional (CCP) Exp. November 2024 WorldatWork

Global Remuneration Professional (GRP) Exp. November 2024 WorldatWork

Professional in Human Resources (PHR) Exp. February 2024

Human Resources Certification Institute (HRCI)

Tableau Desktop 2019 Certified Associate (expired) Exp. October 2021

Tableau

Skills

- Base pay design and administration
- Job analysis, documentation, and evaluation
- Incentive compensation program management
- HRIS integration and administration
- ATS implementation, administration
- LMS implementation, administration
- Talent onboarding process development and management
- People program analysis and evaluation
- Data cleaning and manipulation
- Process improvement, design, and automation
- People team management

Software Experience

- R programming
- Shiny app development
- RStudio IDE
- BambooHR HRIS
- Greenhouse.io ATS
- Culture Amp
- Salary.com CompAnalyst
- UltiPro HRIS (UKG)
- iCIMS ATS
- Fuse LXP
- Cornerstone OnDemand LMS
- Qualtrics